Adult Education Association (AEA-USA)/American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) Records
Adult Education Association (AEA-USA)/American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) Records
1924-1994
Adult Education Association.
44 linear ft.
The Adult Education Association of the U.S.A. (AEA-USA) was formed in 1951 by the merger of the American Association for Adult Education (supported by the Carnegie Foundation) and the Department of Adult Education of the National Education Association. In 1982, the AEA-USA combined with the National Association of Public School Adult Educators (NAPSAE) to become the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE). The collection contains material from both organizations.
Correspondents significant for their importance within the AEA-USA, the volume of the material in the collection, or presence of their papers among the manuscript holdings at Syracuse University include: Andrew Hendrickson, Glenn S. Jensen, Eugene I. Johnson, Malcolm S. Knowles, Robert A. Luke, Lois McCarthy, Nicholas P. Mitchell, Hugh G. Pyle, and Paul H. Sheats. Other prominent individuals in the field of adult education whose correspondence is in the collection are: L.H. Adolphson, Leland P. Bradford, Paul H. Durrie, Paul L. Essert, Cyril O. Houle, Herbert C. Hunsaker, Homer H. Kempfer, A.A. Liveright, Fern Long, Howard Y. McClusky, Robert E. Sharer, Robertson Sillars, Grace Stevenson, and Thurman White.
148799
Biographical History
Adult Education Association of the United States (AEA-USA)
The AEA-USA was founded in Columbus, Ohio, in May 1951 as the result of the joint efforts of the American Association for Adult Education (supported by the Carnegie Foundation) and the Department of Adult Education of the National Education Association. These two organizations dissolved in 1951 and their memberships joined to form the membership of the new organization with offices in Chicago, Illinois. The purpose of the organization was to unite all professional and non-professional adult educators in a single national organization to facilitate communication in the emerging field of adult education. In accordance with this goal the AEA formed the subsidiary Council of National Organizations for Adult Education (CNO) in 1952 in order "to establish closer communication and exchange of experience between organizations and individuals working in different fields."
Gradually the goals of AEA-USA expanded to encompass all activities designed "to further the acceptance of education as a process continuing through-out life; to afford opportunities to professional and non-professional adult educators to increase their competence; to receive and disseminate information about adult education; to promote a balanced development of educational services for adults; and to cooperate with adult education agencies internationally." In order to lobby effectively for the moral and financial support of adult education, the offices of the organization were moved to Washington, D.C., in 1964.
AEA-USA offered general, student, professional, and organizational memberships. Member services included periodicals, special publications, field service, consultation, reference services, and the membership directory. Standing committees included Annual Nominations and Elections, Membership and Field Services, Publications, Social Philosophy, Finance and Development, and Legislative Policy. The wide areas of AEA interest were also reflected in its commissions and sections. Commissions included the Commission on Research in Adult Education, the Council of State Associations, the Commission of Professors of Adult Education, and the Commission on Adult Basic Education, while sections included Armed Forces Education and Training, Community College Adult Education, Correctional Institutions, International Affairs, Liberal Adult Education, and Religious Adult Education, among others.
Other activities of the organization included a clearinghouse of information, a referral center, an annual national conference, publications, and its commissions, councils, and special sections, which conduct research and hold workshops. The two regular publications of the association were Adult Leadership (monthly) for general members and Adult Education (quarterly) for professional members.
American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE)
In 1982, the AEA-USA merged with the National Association of Public School Adult Educators (NAPSAE) to become the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE), which is the name under which the organization operates as of this writing. The AAACE's mission statement is "to provide leadership for the field of adult and continuing education by expanding opportunities for adult growth and development; unifying adult educators; fostering the development and dissemination of theory, research, information, and best practices; promoting identity and standards for the profession; and advocating relevant public policy and social change initiatives."
AAACE maintains seven commissions that represent general areas of interest in the field (e.g. International Adult Education, Adult Basic Education and Literacy), and twenty-six units that represent specific focus areas (e.g. Correctional Institutions, GED Test Administrators, History and Philosophy of Adult Education, Religious Education, Special Learning Needs, Women's Issues, Status, and Education). As of this writing, AAACE continues publication of Adult Education Quarterly and also publishes a second, practitioner-oriented journal, Adult Learning.
[June 2007]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Adult Education Association (AEA-USA)/American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) Records consists of three separate accessions which have been processed to varying degress and which are not integrated. Box numbering is sequential order across all three parts. There is considerable overlap between the three parts in terms of both dates and subject matter.
Part I, 1924-1968 (18 linear ft)
This accession is the most fully processed. It consists entirely of records relating to the AEA-USA. It is divided into Correspondence, Organizational records, and Writings. Besides correspondence, there is printed material including ditto and mimeographed material, photocopy, published material, and newspaper clippings; one volume of trial balance sheets; one journal; and typescript copy for periodical publications of the AEA. The inclusive dates of these papers are ca. 1924-1968, but the bulk of the material is dated 1951 to 1967. The few materials dated prior to 1951 were generated by the American Association for Adult Education, a predecessor of the Adult Education Association, which dissolved and transmitted its records to the AEA in 1951.
Correspondence, 1951-1968, includes incoming and outgoing letters, memoranda, and telegrams, arranged chronologically. Correspondence dated only by year is found at the beginning of the January folder for that year. Undated correspondence is placed at the end of the section. The following correspondents, significant for their importance within the AEA, the volume of their material in the collection, or the presence of their papers among the manuscript holdings of Syracuse University, are heavily represented.
Hendrickson, Andrew
Jensen, Glenn S.
Johnson, Eugene I.
Knowles, Malcolm S.
Luke, Robert A.
McCarthy, Lois
Mitchell, Nicholas P.
Pyle, Hugh G.
Sheats, Paul Henry
Other prominent individuals in the field of adult education whose correspondence is found among the papers of AEA are:
Adolphson, L. H.
Bradford, Leland P.
Durrie, Paul H.
Essert, Paul L.
Houle, Cyril O.
Hunsaker, Herbert C.
Kempfer, Homer H.
Liveright, A. A.
Long, Fern
McClusky, Howard Y.
Sharer, Robert E.
Sillars, Robertson
Stevenson, Grace
White, Thurman
Arrangement of the Organizational records follows, with occasional modification, the subject filing system of the AEA, a copy of which can be found in Box 9. Subject headings used by the AEA were retained where appropriate. New headings were created for materials which did not fit into existing AEA categories. Major headings are arranged alphabetically. Material within these headings is arranged either alphabetically or chronologically, depending upon the nature of the material. Although any one folder may contain a variety of types of materials, correspondence and printed material predominate. Major headings of importance to the re-searcher and containing the largest amounts of material are:
American Association for Adult Education
Business and Finance
Committees
Conference
Files
Delegate Assembly
Membership
Project Task Force
Proposals
Publications
Sections
Notebooks
Box 6 contains some materials from 1924 to 1951 of the American Association for Adult Education and of the Carnegie Corporation. Also part of the collection is some material on the Council of National Organizations (CNO), a subsidiary of AEA-USA, and the National Association of Public School Adult Educators (NAPSAE), an independent organization with which the AEA-USA merged in 1982.
Notebooks are arranged chronologically, following the pattern by which they were kept by the AEA. The material includes minutes, memoranda, working papers, policy statements, reports, proposals, and rosters. Undated pieces are placed at the end of the group. The notebook material overlaps material in the other organizational records. For example, papers relating to the AEA executive committee are found under Notebooks, as well as under Committees. Additional materials of importance are the working papers and minutes of the publication committee and the general office memoranda for 1952 and 1953.
Writings are arranged under the headings of articles, book reviews, copy for Adult Education and Adult Leadership, and speeches. Articles were written by officers of the AEA and are arranged alphabetically according to the authors' surnames. There is one folder of book reviews, dated 1958. Copy is arranged alphabetically by titles of the publications and chronologically within each title. Speeches, both those delivered by AEA officers or by speakers at meetings sponsored by the AEA, are arranged alphabetically by the speakers' surnames.
Part II, 1950-1994 (19 linear ft)
Part II consists of records from the AEA-USA and from the AAACE and has received only minimal processing. Material in this accession covers the following topics: activities, affiliations, annual reports, board of directors meeting minutes, budgets, commissions, committees, conferences, constitution and bylaws, councils, delegate assembly, directories, leadership rosters, manuals, mission statement, publications, sections, files of AAACE president Wendell Smith, subject correspondence, task forces, and units/divisions.
Part III, 1952-1991 (7 linear ft)
Part III consists of historical files, office files, and publications; it spans the complete life of AAACE and thus includes material from all three organizations involved (AEA-USA, NAPSAE, and AAACE). Like Part II, Part III has received only minimal processing. Historical files are divided into AAACE 1982-1986 and AEA 1965-1982; this material includes budgets, conference material, constitutions and bylaws, proposals, published material, reports, surveys, and other material. Office files are divided into AAACE 1983-1987 and AEA 1958-1982; these include reports, meeting minutes (committee and Board of Directors), conference material, reports, publications, correspondence, newsletters, and mailings, among other things. Publications contains AAACE monographs and periodicals, AEA monographs and periodicals, and NAPSAE monographs and periodicals.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing of all adult education collections. In particular, see also the following:
Organizations
Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) Records
Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) Records
Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE) Records
National Association of Public School Adult Educators (NAPSAE) Records
National University Extension Association (NUEA) Records
Individuals
Andrew Hendrickson Papers
Joseph W. Jacques Interviews
Alexander A. Liveright Papers
Robert E. Sharer Papers
Paul H. Sheats Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Adolphson, L. H.; Bradford, Leland Powers, 1905-; Durrie, Paul H.; Essert, Paul L.; Hendrickson, Andrew, 1899-; Houle, Cyril Orvin, 1913-; Hunsaker, Herbert Cason, 1898-; Jensen, Glenn S.; Johnson, Eugene I.; Kempfer, Homer H.; Knowles, Malcolm Sheperd, 1913-; Liveright, A. A. (Alexander Albert), 1907-; Long, Fern, 1905-; Luke, Robert A.; McCarthy, Lois.; McClusky, Howard Y., 1900-1982.; Mitchell, Nicholas Pendleton, 1911-; Pyle, Hugh G.; Sharer, Robert E., 1900-; Sheats, Paul H., 1907-1984.; Smith, Wendell L.; Sillars, Robertson.; Stevenson, Grace Thomas, 1900-; White, Thurman J.; Adult Education Association, Archives.; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education -- Archives.; National Association for Public and Continuing Adult Education.; National Association for Public School Adult Education.; National Education Association of the United States. -- Department of Adult Education.; Adult education quarterly.; Adult leadership.; Adult education -- United States.; Educators -- United States.; Agendas (administrative records); Annual reports.; Articles.; Budgets.; Constitutions.; Correspondence.; Directories.; Manuals (instructional materials); Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Reports.; Speeches (documents)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Adult Education Association of the U.S.A., 1968-1970.
Inventory
- [Part I] Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1951-1956 (Jun); 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Jul)-1958 (Mar); 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Apr)-1961; 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1965; 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1968; undated; 7 folders (Box 5)
- [Part I] Organizational records
  - Adult Education Association of Greater Washington, D.C., 1963-1967 (Box 5)
  - AEA Core Organizational Services, 1954 (Box 5)
  - AEA Direction Finding Process, 1957-1959 (Box 5)
  - AEA Handbook on Adult Education Organization, 1955 (Box 5)
  - AEA History, 1951 (Box 5)
  - AEA Policy Digest, 1957 (Box 6)
  - AEA Reorganization, 1957 (Box 6)
  - Adult Educational Needs, 1956 (Box 6)
  - Adult Education Week, 1963 (Box 6)
  - American Association for Adult Education
    - Annual Meeting Programs, 1927-1936 (Box 6)
    - Carnegie Corporation Adult Education Memos, 1924-1926 (Box 6)
    - Directors' Annual Report, 1949 (Box 6)
    - Executive Board, Minutes and Records, 28 Apr 1947 - 20 Dec 1948 (Box 6)
    - Executive Board, Minutes and Records, 15 Feb 1949 - 14 May 1951 (Box 6)
    - Income Tax, 1926-1949 (Box 6)
    - Journal, 1926-1951 (Box 6)
    - Trial Balance Sheets, 1926-1949 (Package 1)
  - American Federation of Labor, 1952-1955 (Box 6)
  - Book of the Month Project, 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - Business and Finance
    - Advance Education Fund, 1955 (Box 7)
    - Advertising
      - Accounts, 1958-1959 (Box 7)
      - Adult Leadership, 1958 (Box 7)
      - Delinquent, 1959 (Box 7)
      - Accounts - Adult Leadership and Adult Education, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
    - Annual audit, 1954-1964; 11 folders (Box 7)
    - Bowery Savings Bank, 1955-1964 (Box 7)
    - Budgets, 1948-1965; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Constitution and Articles of Incorporation, 1951-1966 (Box 8)
    - Employee service records, 1953-1957 (Box 8)
    - Endowment Fund, 1953-1962; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Exhibits, 1954-1957 (Box 8)
    - Filing system, 1967
    - Financial statements, 1951-1962; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Fund for Adult Education, 1951-1965 (Box 8)
    - Headquarters move, 1963 (Box 9)
    - Job descriptions, undated (Box 9)
    - McKinsey & Co., Management Consultant's Report, 1953 (Box 9)
    - New office space, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Personnel & salary policy, 1951-1952 (Box 9)
  - Council of National Organizations
    - Interrelationship of CNO & AEA, 1953-1960 (Box 9)
    - Policy papers, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Program Guide, 1954 (Box 9)
    - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1960; Reports, Memberships, Correspondence (Box 9)
    - Commission of Professors of Adult Education, 1960 (Box 9)
  - Committees
    - Adult Education Organizations, 1967 Jan-Jul (Box 9)
    - Area Projects, 1952 (Box 9)
    - Committee on Committees, Commissions and Sections, 1952-1960 (Box 9)
    - Conference and Consultation, 1954 (Box 10)
    - Education of the Foreign Born, 1952
    - Executive Committee, 1951-1958; 8 folders (Box 10)
    - Executive Committee, 1959-1965; 7 folders (Box 11)
    - Field Development Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 11)
    - Finance and Development, 1954; 1959-1962; 7 folders (Box 11)
    - Future Activities, 1956 (Box 12)
    - Legislative Policy, 1962-1966; 11 folders (Box 12)
    - Membership and Field Services, 1955; 1961-1964 (Jun); 5 folders (Box 12)
    - Membership and Field Services, 1964 (Jul)-1968; 4 folders (Box 13)
    - NEA and AEA Joint Committee, 1954 (Box 13)
    - National Organizing Committee, 1950-1951 (Box 13)
    - Nominations and Elections, 1955; 1959-1962; 5 folders (Box 13)
    - Nominations and Elections, 1963-1966; 4 folders (Box 14)
    - Personnel Information Exchange, 1955 (Box 14)
    - Promotion Committee, 1954 (Box 14)
    - Publications, 1954-1956; 1962-1966; 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Resolution Committee, 1953 (Box 15)
    - Social Philosophy, 1950-1957; 1960,; 1962-1966; 7 folders (Box 15)
    - Steering Committee, 1955-1963 (Box 15)
    - Structure, 1960-1962 (Box 15)
    - Study and Membership, 1956 (Box 15)
    - Wamcke Committee on Membership, 1966-1967 (Box 15)
  - Conference files
    - Adult Education Satellite Conference, 1966 Dec 13-14 (Box 15)
    - American Library Association Adult Education Workshop Materials, 1955-1956 (Box 15)
    - Arizona Adult Education Association Meeting, 1967 (Box 15)
    - CNO Meeting, 1959 (Box 15)
    - CNO
      - Experiment in Liberal Curriculum Development for National Organization Leadership - Report to FAE, 1959-1960 (Box 15)
      - Experiment in Liberal Curriculum Development for National Organization Leadership - Anthology of Readings, 1960 (Box 16)
    - Curbstone Conference, 1955 (Box 16)
    - Galaxy Conference of Adult Education Organizations, 1967 Sep 17-18 (Box 16)
    - Health Services and Community Organization, 1965 (Box 16)
    - Inter-Association Meetings, 1962-1964 (Box 16)
    - Local and Regional Workshop, 1960 (Box 16)
    - NAPSAE Conference, 1953; 1954,; 1955,; 1956; 4 folders (Box 16)
    - National conferences
      - National Conference, 1952; 1953; 2 folders (Box 16)
      - National Conference, 1954-1960; includes pre-conference studies from 1955; 8 folders (Box 17)
      - National Conference, 1961; 1962,; 1964,; 1966,; 1967, Jan-Oct; 7 folders (Box 18)
      - National Conference, 1967, Nov-Dec and; undated; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - National Congress on the Rights and Responsibilities of the Public in Commercial Broadcasting, 1966 Dec 1-2 (Box 19)
    - National Organizations and Agencies with a Primary Adult Education Function Conference, 1960 (Box 19)
    - North American Conference on Adult Education, 1967 Oct 22-25 (Box 19)
    - Regional Conference, 1965; 1966; 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Urban Affairs, 1962 (Box 19)
  - Delegate Assembly
    - Members and materials, 1951 (Box 20)
    - Reports, handbook, notes, misc., 1952 Oct 22-23 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence (Box 20)
    - Working papers, 1953 (Box 20)
    - Roster, 1953 (Box 20)
    - Resolutions, 1953-1954; including correspondence on same (Box 20)
    - Resolutions, 1953 Oct 28 (Box 20)
    - Minutes, 1953 Oct 26-29 (Box 20)
    - Reports, handbook, correspondence, minutes, misc., 1954 Oct 9-10 (Box 20)
    - Reports, memo, correspondence, misc., 1954 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 21)
    - Working papers, 1955 (Box 21)
    - Roster and attendance, 1955 (Box 21)
    - Resolutions, 1955 (Box 21)
    - Minutes, 1955 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, resolutions, rosters, 1956 (Box 21)
    - Working papers, 1956 (Box 21)
    - Minutes, 1956 (Box 21)
    - Handbook, 1957 (Box 22)
    - Agenda, correspondence, reports, misc., 1957 (Box 22)
    - Correspondence, reports, handbook, misc., 1958 (Box 22)
    - Checklist, handbook, reports, 1959 (Box 22)
    - Handbook, index, reports, 1960 (Box 22)
    - Agenda, handbook, index, roster of participants, 1961 (Box 22)
    - Report, 1962 (Box 22)
    - Handbook, resolutions, 1963 (Box 22)
    - Agenda, report, resolutions, roster, 1964 (Box 22)
  - Founding Assembly, general materials, 1949-1953; undated; 4 folders (Box 23)
  - Long-range plans
    - Three-Year Plan, 1953 (Box 23)
    - Ten-Year Plan, 1954 (Box 23)
    - Five-Year Plan, 1956; 3 folders (Box 23, 24)
  - Membership
    - Adult education councils and associations, 1959 (Box 24)
    - Attitudes of non-members toward AEA, 1953 (Box 24)
    - Development program, 1954-1955 (Box 24)
    - Directory, 1965-1967 (Box 24)
    - Directory of national organizations, 1954 (Box 24)
    - Drive, 1958 (Box 24)
    - Form letters and promotional material, 1952-1967; 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Joint membership state associations, 1952-1958 (Box 24)
    - Lists, 1956-1968 (Box 24)
    - Mailing lists, 1955-1956 (Box 25)
    - Membership characteristics study, 1956 Apr (Box 25)
    - Promotion, 1964-1965; 1966-1967; 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Records, 1954-1967 (Box 25)
    - Recruitment activities, 1956 (Box 25)
    - Regional associations, 1957 (Box 25)
    - Response to Thurman White letters, 1966 Jun-Oct (Box 25)
    - State associations, 1957; 1964-1967; 3 folders (Box 25)
    - State coordinators, 1953-1967 (Box 25)
    - Surveys, 1953-1955 (Box 25)
    - Urban associations, 1967 (Box 25)
  - National Commission on Adult Literacy, 1952-1956; 1957-1961; 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Project Task Force
    - General, 1965 (Box 26)
    - Colorado, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Georgia, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Illinois, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Indiana, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Iowa, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Kansas, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Kentucky, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Louisiana, 1963 (Box 26)
    - Michigan, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - Missouri, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - New England, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - New Jersey, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - New York, 1962-1963 (Box 26)
    - North Carolina, 1962-1963 (Box 27)
    - North Dakota, 1962-1963 (Box 27)
    - Ohio, 1962-1963 (Box 27)
    - Oklahoma, 1962-1963 (Box 27)
    - Pennsylvania, 1962-1964 (Box 27)
    - Region IV (Maryland, Delaware, Virginia, West Virginia, District of Columbia), 1963 (Box 27)
    - Utah, 1963 (Box 27)
    - Washington, 1963 (Box 27)
  - Proposals
    - AEA - ALA Adult Education Resource Center, 1952-1953 (Box 27)
    - AEA Purposes and Structure, 1955-1963 (Box 27)
    - AEA Research, 1956 (Box 27)
    - AEA Self Study, 1955 (Box 27)
    - Adult Education Policies Commission, 1956 (Box 27)
    - Adult Education Program Stimulation Through Local School Districts, 1956 (Box 27)
    - Adult Education Trends Study, 1959 (Box 27)
    - Citizen Education Project, 1958 (Box 27)
    - Citizen Involvement and Policy Making in Adult Education, 1956 (Box 27)
    - Clinics for Citizen Evaluation of Communication Media, undated (Box 27)
    - Cooperative Program of Nation-wide In-Service Training for Educators of Adults, undated (Box 27)